Staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall, and he will be the light of
the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled. All who dwell on the earth will fall
down and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5. The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless
Haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
In our time, many years.
to break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism,
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen De Young,
post this live Colin show,
focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experience.
by mankind throughout history. Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, all of you, dragon slayers, giant killers, slayers of serpents,
and stompers on scorpions. You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Yung, is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana, where it's
probably 100 degrees right now. And I'm Father-Injust Stephen Damick in
a male's Pennsylvania where we still have winter.
And we are live.
And if you are listening to us live,
you can call us at 855-237-2346,
just like the voice of Steve just said.
And you can talk to us live.
We're gonna get your calls starting in the second half
of the show and our own beloved,
Matyska Trudy will be taking your calls.
So our Catholic friends and some of our Protestant friends,
more and more of you as I understand it.
And also our fellow Orthodox Christians in Finland.
And the place where I quite want to be have already begun lent this year, and while
it's still a few weeks away from most orthodox, it is on our minds for sure.
The triodian is about to begin.
That said, there are some Christians, and you know who you are, who think that Great
Lent is a medieval invention with no basis in the Scriptures, that the seasonal asceticism
of fasting in particular is some kind of attempt at earning one's way to heaven.
firmly established before in this podcast that we believe in works righteousness. But what if we told
you that Lent and its constituent practices are very firmly rooted in the scriptures. And what if we
told you that its endpoint might not be what you think. And what if we told you that Gavin Rossdale
is way more talented than his ex-wife and Bush is a great band? I would agree with that for sure.
Maybe.
The other two questions you're shaky on, but that one I'm good.
Well, you know, I'm still a little, I didn't sleep very well last night and so like my,
my Morpheus voice is not, I couldn't do the, you know, what if I told, I, it's just not
coming for me tonight.
So I'm a little off my game, but I can only assume that if you didn't sleep at all last
night, you were thinking about almond delight.
Yes, that seems reasonable to assume.
Yeah.
I don't know if you could even still buy it.
So I mean.
that might keep you up.
I don't know.
I'm going to look that up real quick.
I'll get back to you.
Live radio everybody.
That's right.
I'm in Delight cereal.
But so, uh, yeah, the, the, uh, there may be some folks out there,
especially among our Protestant friends who think Lent is that special time of year when Catholics quit smoking.
Hmm.
or briefly give up chocolate.
If you're down here in Southern Louisiana, it's all the sudden they're a fish fries everywhere on Fridays.
But Greatland in all of its details is it's celebrating the Orthodox Church actually has
a history reaching back into the apostolic period that we're going to talk about tonight.
And there are various reasons why more...
a little bit in the West. I remember 20 odd years ago now. There was a, I don't know if he's
still living or not, but there was a Franciscan friar on EWTN. And he was from Brooklyn, and very
much from Brooklyn. And at the beginning of Lent, he was talking about Lent. And he kind of went
on this rant.
doing the whole, why can't you Catholics fast? The Orthodox, they fast? Why can't you
fast? Right? This whole thing that I still remember. And a lot of a lot of the things
still surrounding Lent, even in the West, imply more of the Orthodox practice. Right?
Right, so carnival.
literally comes from
Karnas, meat and
Valle farewell in Latin. Yeah.
Yeah. I mean, here in the
Lehigh Valley, we have something
called Fost Knox, which I know
exists outside the Lehigh Valley as well.
And it's literally a donut that you can get the day before
Ash Wednesday. And I remember seeing
some news article or something, you know,
these little human interest articles where the writer said
writer said something like
some see
this has to do with the beginning of Lent. I'm like, the name literally means fasting eve. What do
you mean some say? Like, at the whole point of these donuts is like, use up all of the lard and
the butter and, you know, whatever. The day before. Yeah. Well, in a course, there are some small
reserved private family celebrations down here in Louisiana called Marty Grah.
I've heard that, yes, which...
religious and very pious always. But that's French for fat Tuesday, right? For the same
reason, right? You didn't have refrigeration. So you ate everything through parties and
ate everything before Ash Wednesday, right? So that because it wouldn't keep, that you
weren't going to eat it during a lint.
But so that said, there's a...
There's a lot of things tied up in why for some, if not many, if not most of our
Protestant friends, why let seems like some kind of weird accretion. And we're
going to get into that over the course of tonight, you know, kind of a
understanding what asceticism is, what the purpose is, where it comes from.
From to begin here, though, in our first half, we're going to talk about the number 40 because
of course, Great Lent goes for 40 days.
It's the 40 days before Holy Week, before Pascha, before the Passover.
Um, yet I'm sure at some point during let on this show I will go into my rant about.
why we don't just translate the word PASKA as Passover in our hymns and that kind of thing,
so that they will make sense to people. But that's not tonight. So we're going to talk about
this number 40 and 40 days and the significance of that. This is one of these biblical numbers.
when you read through, you don't even have to get very far in the old test.
before you start noticing that lots of things come in sevens, and lots of things come in 40s,
and lots of things come in 12s, right? For example, and then 70 or 72, right? There are these
certain numbers that keep recurring, and one of those, one of those is course is 40. So before we
get into...
a big list of examples of where 40 shows up in the scriptures and start working
through and talking about some of those and the themes that emerge out of
that. We have to talk for a minute about the number 40 itself. So we've talked
about on several occasions the number 70 on the show and how it's like 70
sometimes
72, right? That there is this sort of wiggle between 70 and 72. And how a lot of that has
to do with when you don't have numerals, which neither Hebrew nor Greek have numerals,
and those of course the languages in which the scriptures were written, air may echo
also no numerals.
Yeah, they're just, they just use letters to designate numbers.
these letters to indicate numbers and
That means, de facto, even if you want to, you can't be that precise.
This is one of the problems with the modernist version of a literal reading of the Old Testament
that tries to take every number literally.
You very quickly find that, for example, between the Greek and the Hebrew, there are radical
differences every time there's a number.
Yes.
as Goliath, for instance.
Yeah.
66 or 9.9. And across the board, every place we find numbers, they're different. Right. And
even, I pointed this out in another context recently, even the Romans, Romans kind of renowned
for their record keeping, had Roman numerals and everything. Right. How many troops was a
a centurion in command of.
This is a trick question 80 80
Dang it
Etymology for fails me again. Yes exactly. No, but that's what it is. It's a commander of a hundred and he didn't have a hundred people under him
Yeah
They had another position called a Kili arc a
Thousand
You're a six century is under him
So 480 plus the insurance
Man!
Right. So all this is to say,
Yeah, numbers don't don't mean the mathematical numbers the way that we mean them.
Right. In the ancient world, they didn't feel the need for that kind of precision on these things.
Right. Things get rounded, they get rounded up and down a little bit.
Right. So saying 70 and saying 72,
there was not a huge difference or need for precision in that regard.
Right. In the ancient world.
Same is true with 40 because you also get 40 and 42 doing the same thing. And just like
with 72, which is 6 times 12, 42 is 6 times 7. It's 6 7s. Yeah. 7, as we've talked about
on the 4 on the show.
7 is
is seem to be a number that represents completion or wholeness.
Yeah, which is why we have seven days in a week.
Right.
But the reason why seven is that number is because there are seven planets
counting the sun and moon.
I'll just leave that there.
Did you just deplanetize Pluto again?
Oh, I just deplanetize the whole.
Yeah, I know.
So because
talking about early astronomy, slashe astrology, right? The stuff you can see without powerful
tell us. Right. And so the distinction there was between, right? The quote unquote fixed stars
in their constellations that followed this orderly pattern. And then those are there. And then
And there are also these other objects, right in the heavens, that they didn't think of
as objects.
beings, frankly, in the heavens, that did not follow the same kind of orderly path with the stars.
And those were the sun, the moon, mercury, Venus, Mars, Jupiter and Saturn.
That were observed. So they saw these
is moving around.
Wondrous.
Yes.
So.
And that's what planets means.
Right.
Planetis and Greek means wanderers.
So they said, oh, there's these other bodies
that wander through the heavens.
But if you have all seven of them, right,
then that's completion.
And so you get the seven branched candlestand
in the tabernacle.
and later in the temple, seven lights.
Right? That's the cosmos. Right? That's the sky. It's that connection. So if you had
seven sevens, right? Seven times seven, seven sevens, it's 49, that would be sort of
complete completion. Right. But if you have six sevens, 42 or
40, right? If you have six sevens, then that's not so much in completion as sort of we're
nearing the end of the cycle, right? Yeah. Something is being prepared for. Yeah. Almost
there. Stay on target for porkers dead too soon. Um, and done wrong by being given the name
porkens. Let me I know like right? How politically correct is that?
the overweight guy. I mean, yeah, like George Lucas. I mean, George Lucas is not exactly
skinny himself. Right. Yeah. I mean, this is, I mean, although back then, even that he
wasn't that skinny. But, yeah. So there is this, you get to the end of the sixth, seven,
and there is then this anticipation. Right. So sort of now we're going to begin this
final cycle. Now we're going to bring this to
completion. And so you have this sense of preparation and anticipation and
something that's about now to happen. So we'll start now with some
examples in the scriptures. So one of the first really prominent uses of 40
happens in Genesis 7 and 8 with the flood story. So God of course...
creates the world in Genesis 1 and the first couple verses of chapter 2 in
seven days, right? Really creates it in six and then rests on the
seventh day he's enthroned. So there is this completion there, right? But then with the
flood, God unmakes the world. Right? So if you read the language of the flood,
And um
All of the things that happen in the first three days fall apart.
So first on day three, God had separated the dry land from the water.
The flood comes.
That is gone.
On the second day, God had separated the waters above like the sky and the waters below
the sea.
That separation disappears.
The gates of the heavens are open.
the gates of the deeper, opened, and water.
And so the world gets uncreated, but for the sort of microcosm of the creation that exists within the arc.
Noah and his wife and his sons and their wives and the animals.
That little microcosm of creation survives.
And the flood goes on for 40 days and 40 nights.
And then once the 40 days are completed, now there is this anticipation.
Now the preparation is complete.
Now the world is going to be recreated.
It's going to begin again with no end to family and the animals from the ark.
example of this from Genus.
comes in Genesis 50 verse 3 and that is the mummifying of Jacob.
Yeah, although usually that's not the word you see in most translations. I think it's
embalming. Yeah. Use em bomb. But I think did you claim mummifying Jacob as a band and or
album name? Oh absolutely. During our previous discussion. Yeah, yeah. Oh yeah. Yeah, that's totally
my next band. Yeah. Yeah.
What's your break up with that last band?
Well, um, could be a side project.
So like audio slave.
Yeah, there you go.
Actually Soundguard and broken up at that point.
So it raised against the machine.
So complete fail.
That was not a side project.
It's a perfect circle.
A perfect side project.
Mr. Bungle was a side project.
Anyway.
Um, so, uh,
Right, Jacob.
Israel the person, right, has died in Egypt after going there
to escape
the famine that came on the land of Canaan, but
Jacob had his son's promise that he would be buried in Canaan with his father's Abraham in Isaac and
so
Genesis 50 verse 3
Jacob is mummified
and Egypt so that he can be brought back to
brought back to Canaan, right? And this wasn't typical Egyptian
mummification in the sense that it didn't serve the same purpose.
Yeah, it wasn't about, you know, making him alive in some way in
the world of the dead, you know, or big, you know, like burial in
in a big
royal tomb or you know there is no pyramid of Jacob. Right. It was it was for the purpose
of being able to transport his body. Yeah, because you can't frankly you can't move bodies
over long distances right after someone's died and the bodies stand tacked. Right. Unless
they're in Balmton somewhere. Right. And that's actually I don't know if you know this
fun fact everybody. That's when in Balming the whole in Balming industry really took off in
the United States was at the end of the Civil War.
get him to bring soldiers from the battlefield.
Maybe two or they're going to bury him.
Yeah.
So, but there's this 40-day preparation period, right,
where his body is prepared to make this final journey
to rest with his fathers.
Then moving into Exodus, of course, famously,
Israel spent
40 years, wandering around the Sinai Peninsula,
insert joke about GPS, right?
But that's not actually why, of course.
The reason why was because of their sin.
Yeah, I mean, they showed up at the Promised Land,
and like, oh, giants, yeah, no, we don't need to obey God.
Hard pass, yeah.
Exactly.
Okay, fine.
you
kids are going to get it. Even though it hadn't been spelled out yet, the fact that they were
going to wander for 40 years is first mentioned in Exodus 1635. And so this introduces another element
in terms of the 40-day period. We've been talking about the anticipation and the preparation.
In this case, it's not anticipation or preparation for these people to enter the land because
they're not going to enter the land. Yeah. Right. It is for one generation of these people to die.
Right. So there is, in view here, the idea of atonement for sin, atonement in what sense? Atonement,
in the sense that the nation of Israel, which is made up of all of these people, has to be purified
certain wicked members.
Yeah, I mean, purifying by basically making an intergenerational move.
Yeah, shift by letting them die.
And this is merciful in the sense that these people got to live out their lives.
Yeah.
With God feeding them and clothing them and caring for them in the wilderness.
They got to live out their lives.
He didn't have them all killed he didn't kill them all the ground in openness
swallow them all, right, for their sin. But all actual options in the old testament.
Yes, all things that happened in the immediate vicinity of in the Torah. Yeah. Yeah.
Other people who did things. But in this case, right, they're given this mercy of being able to live
out their lives. But the the the Israelites as a whole have to be purified. And that's what a
the tone man is really bad is about purification and so...
that would be purified by the death of these members,
but that has now sin and purification in view
with this 40 day or with a 40,
with the number 40 in this case.
Probably the most important example
is the one we're gonna talk about next,
at least the most important for Lent
for what we're talking about in terms of Lent.
Because a lot of the future references to 40
to come back to this one. And that has to do with Moses at Mount Sinai. And the number 40 comes up
here twice because Moses goes up the mountain twice. In the first case, Moses goes up the mountain.
He's there for 40 days.
He receives, he writes down the book of the covenant, right?
He gets the tablets from God, right? And he comes down and he finds the people
with the golden calf. We've talked about that on the show before. We won't go back in a detail,
but you can go back and listen to our Dollar Tree episode.
To get on...
the gory details of what they were actually doing. The tablets are smashed, signifying that
they've already broken the covenant that they agreed to. So that first 40-day period
is Moses preparing to receive the law, to receive the covenant, to receive the Torah,
to deliver the Torah to the people. Right? It is as this preparatory element. Right? But now,
After all that's been broken after...
Moses meets out justice for the Golden Caff incident. Right? Become to this point where
God is at the point after the Golden Caff incident where he says to Moses, you know what?
Let's just wipe out these folks and we'll start over Moses with your descendants. You'll be like
the new Abraham. Right? We'll just restart this and I'll give you and your seed, the Land of
Canaan, right? You're descended from Abraham, so.
And Moses intercedes for the people, despite their sin, and he goes back up the mountain,
and he spends another 40 days.
And during this 40 days in the second visit, Moses does not eat any food or drink any water
for the whole 40 days.
He fasts.
He's fasting.
And he's fasting as part of
this intercession for the people, for the sins of the people.
Aaron fasting. Right. He is essentially repenting for them. Right. He's taking actions of repentance
for them. He was up on the mountain. He didn't worship the golden calf. Yeah. He's not, unlike his
brother, he's not located in what went on down down there at the bottom of the fountain. Right.
But he is on their behalf and he's widened solidarity with them, hoping they're also fasting and
and repenting, right?
that on their on their behalf. And what emerges out of that second trip up the
mountain is a reassurance of forgiveness. Is God again giving the tablets to Moses
and saying, no, this story isn't over. This is going to continue. Right. And so
there is both a preparatory element because at that point it's okay now leave
Sinai, right? And head for Canaan, right? We're going to do this now. So there's that preparatory
anticipatory element, but there's also that element of repentance in that 40 days. Those
become connected. And in Deuteronomy chapter 9, Deuteronomy, the book of Deuteronomy, is Moses sort of last
Lengthy, Sermon or Hop...
or proclamation, whatever we want to call it, to the people of Israel before his death.
And in Deuteronomy chapter 9, specifically in verses 11 and 18, he mentions these two visits
to the top of Mount Sinai. But in that chapter in general, he's narrating these events
Right. And talking about what he did, reminding them of what happened. Right. Because the people he's talking to
The generation that did that is gone, right?
He's talking to the next generation.
And saying, remember, this is what happened, right?
And talking about his own fasting and his own repentance, right?
And seeking forgiveness for the people there.
So then some more examples in Numbers 13, verse 25.
The numbers of course is every...
favorite book of the Bible. There's some close to hidden in there people. There is. There is
really important stuff in there. In between the numbers. The numbers are important too, but it's
not as obvious how and why they're important. There are chunks of it that are not an easy read.
We'll get that. Yeah. But so when the spies are sent to go and check out the land of Canaan,
and they're sent for 40 days.
For days, again, this is anticipatory.
This is preparatory.
We're going and seeing what's there is preparation to go in.
Right?
And so part of the problem there, part of the short circuit there that's identified as
sinful and a real problem is that most of the spies come back and say, yeah, we need
to call this off.
so
them that preparatory period is not a preparatory period, right? Because what they were preparing
for they want to call off. They want to abandon. Right. It's only Joshua and Caleb who
agree with everything else that other spies reported but said, no, with God on our side,
we got this, right? So then in Joshua, Joshua 14, verse 7.
particular Joshua is speaking to the people. And he mentions that when he went as a spy to
spy out the land, he was 40 years old. So his life up to that time had sort of prepared him
for then this part he was going to play. We also see this with Moses's age by the way, Moses
This lived to be 120 and that's 340s.
The first...
40 years of his life, he was living in Pharaoh's household, which was preparatory for the second
40 years of his life when he was living with Jethro, his father-in-law, and taking care of his
herds, which was preparatory for the last 40 years of his life when he led the people out of Egypt.
So leading the people of Israel out of Egypt was Moses' third act that he started when he was 80.
That's what he got down to.
to what we all remember Moses for.
So, but it's these three periods of 40 years.
In the early part of the Book of Judges,
we've talked before about the Book of Judges on this show.
There's no more popular topic among listeners
to this show than the Book of Judges.
especially many layers.
14 through 16.
But, and we've talked about how in judges, the pattern of the book of judges is that it's
showing this decline, this rather steep decline of religion and morals in Israel to show the
necessity of Israel having a king, of a king emerging.
specifically of a king from the tribe of Judah.
specifically pointing to David, right? That's how judges is written. But so the early judges, the first
few judges, you're still near the top of the slope, right? And not quite as bad. Yeah, it's going
to roll down from there down the hill. That is a sys of his reference. And the great thing about
out, since of his jokes is you can tell them over and over again and they get funnier
each time.
But judges, when you look at the first few judges, and you can see this in judges 311,
531, and 828, I'm Jack Vanning being it up tonight.
Yeah.
Just throwing out the references.
But you look at those early judges, every time they're done with their work, judging Israel,
Israel has raced for 40 years.
Right, that's one of the marks that this was a good judge.
Right.
Things are going to go more awry later.
And speaking of people who judged Israel,
First Samuel 418,
this is after Eli, the high priest,
has fallen over and died.
He was the judge of Israel for 40 years.
And if you're reading in first Samuel, you know that Samuel, when he was given by his
mother to God, went and stayed with Eli, the high priest.
It becomes his mentor.
Yeah.
And so Eli's term is sort of this preparatory period for the prophet Samuel to take over
and become the judge of.
the judge of Israel. When we talked about this earlier, Father Andrew was not aware of the way in which
for Samuel makes fun of Eli. Yes, it's a joke that you can only get if you look at the Hebrew.
Yeah. And once again, maybe this is where George Lucas got the idea. But, sure, yes.
So Eli
The way he dies is he falls over at his chair and breaks his neck because he is very obese.
Yeah, it's not a very dignified ending.
Yes, because he is quite obese.
So, there's a baby born after Eli dies.
The reason he fell over at the chair is because he heard that the arc of the covenant had
been captured.
after
We're told about Eli's death.
We're told that this baby is born and is named in English,
like in the King James translation, Ikebod.
Yeah, like Ikebod Crain.
Yeah, which is Ikebod in Hebrew.
And we're told that he's named Ikebod Ikebod
because the glory had departed from Israel
when the ark was captured.
And Havod is indeed a word that means glory.
But the root...
meaning of Havod is heavy or weighty. Yeah, thus the phrase the CS Lewis book, the weight of glory.
Yeah, yeah, that's this idea of sort of substance of heaviness. And so Havod, in addition to
meaning the glory has departed, also means the fat guys gone. Can you imagine that, says Nika
a bod. Yeah, after Eli dies.
So even the Bible picks on poor Ely.
There are lots of puns and stuff like that in the Hebrew that don't get carried over well
into English.
And so the English Bible way less fun.
It's a takeaway for tonight.
Yes.
So later in first Samuel, when Goliath is coming out with a Philistine army and cutting
promos on Saul and the Israelite army, issuing his challenge for someone to fight him.
He does that for 40 days.
Right.
Why is that so significant?
Well
The way this functions in the telling of the story when you drop in that detail, right,
of it, of him, this going on for 40 days or 42 or roughly 40, right?
This goes on for 40 days.
That's again setting up this expectation, setting up this sense of anticipation.
Yeah.
He did it for 40 days.
Oh, something very important is about to happen.
Yeah, something's coming.
That's what the 40 is an indication of.
that some
thing in this case is David. And then David once he becomes king, he's going to reign as king
for 40 years. His son Solomon is going to reign for 40 years. That's not just important in terms
of the parallel with the judges, right? So the judges having granted that rest, that peace for 40 years,
right? It's still anticipatory because
within the book of judges, the early judges, the good judges are pointing to what the
king who comes is going to be like in a positive way.
Yeah.
In an anticipatory way.
The later judges are going to also show us what the king is going to be like, but in
a reverse way.
Right.
Like, anybody but these guys, he's not going to be like this.
He's going to be like the opposite of this.
Right.
So in the same way
Right? Even now that we have David and even now that we have his son Solomon, the fact that they reign for 40 years
Right, then it's six seven. It's not seven. It's not 49 years
It's 40 years
shows that even their reigns are anticipatory of something else. Yeah, they're pointing beyond. It's not oh finally David is here
Right and this is part of
how
the idea of the Davidic Messiah develops, right? Because you could read the
covenant with David in 2 Samuel, I believe 6 Samuel 7, you could read that
covenant with David is just oh one of your sons will sit on the throne forever
right? So just your dynasty isn't going to have an end, period, right? But
But when you bring in this idea of him raining for 40 years, there's this idea of incompletion
but also anticipation.
So it's not just that the line of David is not going to have an end.
It's just going to be a line shooting off into infinity, but that it is going to culminate.
The light of David is leading somewhere and is going to culminate with someone.
that's that's part and parcel of the messianism and this understanding of the
number 40 is part of how that comes into Jewish tradition later in reflection on
David and on Solomon and on David's line. In first Kings 19 verse 8 this is where
Prophet Elijah St. Elias had his big victory at Mount Parmal over the prophets of Vail,
and then falls into this kind of isolated depression where he says to God, you know,
there's no one left but me who still serves you. Why don't you just go ahead and kill me.
We'll call it a day, right? And God of course talks to him about the faithful remnant that
he has preserved at that time and at all times.
But then he goes further than that.
And he has the prophet Elijah, clean himself up,
wash himself up, eat a little food, take this journey of 40 days.
Yeah, with food that lasts for 40 days, too, I recall.
Yeah, to take this journey for 40 days, because at the end of that journey,
God is...
going to reveal himself to the prophet.
And then it's at the end of that 40 day journey that he has
that experience where there's the fire and God's not the fire
and there's the earthquake and God's not the earthquake. And then
there's the in the King James, the still small voice, right.
The quiet, right. And and that's the place where where he
encounters God. But there is this preparatory period. And this is,
This is Delib-
We've never at least set up with the prophet Elijah to make us think back to Moses in the forty days, right on the mountain.
Before this encounter, but he's preparing to meet God and there's this preparatory period.
In Jonah, you could look for example in Jonah three verse four, where Jonah is finally preaching in Nineveh, after finally getting there.
and Jonas preaching remember is
in 40 days the city's toast. Right.
I think it will be over thrown. Over thrown. Yes. Yes.
Toast is good though. I mean, yeah.
Well, I mean, what is overthrown, really mean? Like tossed? Like, what, you know, yeah, I mean, I.
The city's done for it for 40 days. Yeah, I mean, it doesn't, and it doesn't say exactly how God's going to.
Pull that off either, you know, you could saw them in by heaven. Like, saw them in good.
Yeah, yeah, could be no.
Invasive.
Yeah, earthquake.
Yeah.
Yeah. Blood fire, flood fire, the sword, gnats, pestilence bugs,
yeah, rats. So, but they have 40 days. They have 40 days. And
people may want to point out, right, that Jonah doesn't
actually tell them to repent. Then we know from reading the
book of Jonah, that's because Jonah didn't want them to repent.
Yeah, he wanted them to be overthrown. He was looking forward
to the fireworks.
And so he didn't say that, but the very fact that God sent him there before the fact to
announce it implies the possibility of repentance.
Right.
They were really at the point where God was just going to destroy them.
Why warn them?
Yeah.
Right.
Sodom and Gomorrah didn't get a warning.
God sent the angels in to get Latinist family out before it happened, but they didn't go around warning the people of Sodom and Gomorrah.
Yeah, but it was coming. It's crazy that even a have got a warning. Yeah. It's almost like he's super merciful.
Yeah. Yeah. But so Ninova, well, if you know anything about the Assyrians. Oh, yeah.
They're pretty bad.
So, but they're given this 40 days of warning.
And so they use that 40 days.
days to repent. They spend that 40 days repenting much to Jonah's consternation.
Yeah. Right. Jonah ends up telling God, I knew I know what kind of God you are. I knew if
they were pen it, you'd let them off the hook. Right. But so there's 40 day period again.
is that repentance element.
Then jumping to the New Testament, Matthew, in St. Matthew's Gospel, he structures his genealogy
around three sets of 14 generations.
Yeah, so he get 42.
Right.
And there's, ready, has 14 generations from Abraham to David, 14 generations from David
the exile, 14 generations from the exile to the birth of Jesus. And if you go through those
genealogies, you see that in order to get those three sets of 14, St. Matthew has to play
a little fast and loose with the old test of a genealogies.
There's a few guys he skips, but I mean, they're pretty skippable. Yeah, who he skips
there. But also he's deliberately got these numbers in mind.
Yeah, because he wants to present a 42. Yeah.
Um, and so yeah, he finds the most skippable people to skip, but it's, um,
but so why does he do that?
Right. Well, again, contrary to the modernist, literal reading of the Bible, uh,
he's not trying to give an exact genealogical account.
Yeah. He's not trying to pull a fast one on anybody. Right. No. No.
He's
mentioning the specific people he mentions for various reasons. And he set up this set of six
sevens, right? 42, preparation building up to something anticipation. It's all leading up to
the birth of Jesus. Right. Everything from Abraham is building up to the birth of Jesus.
Everything from King David is building up to the birth of Jesus. Everything from the return from
from the Babylonian exile is...
building up to the birth of Jesus. That's what he's making. There's a lot of dramatic tension throughout
the whole Old Testament. If you look for all the forties, which we have been doing. Yeah.
Something's coming. Something's coming. Okay. Still something is coming. Oh, by the way,
something is coming. Yes. Yeah. And in many cases, based on what's coming, you probably should be
repenting. Yeah. Yes. One of the most famous, in fact, if
If I think if we ask to the average church goer, what's
an example of something that goes on for 40 days and 40 nights
in the Bible? Probably the most common answer we'd get would
be about Christ fasting in the wilderness in the desert.
Maybe after the flood, I think if you say 40 days and
40 nights, probably at least the people who know the old
testament a little bit, right, but probably I think more people
I know the new test went through the...
I want to believe.
And so, you know, you can find this in Matthew 4.2, Mark 1 verse 13, Luke 4 verse 2.
Thanks for Accela.
Where it mentions the 40 days and 49s.
Right.
And we talked a little bit in the last episode about how, on one level, Christ is
here sort of recapitulating the experience.
of Israel. Israel spent 40 years in the wilderness. They spent it there grumbling and complaining
about things like food, right? Christ's faces, same tests. In the wilderness, Christ succeeds
where they failed. But this is also a callback to Moses, right? This is also callback to Moses
specifically him fasting from prudent water on the mountain.
Yeah.
How so? Well, this is telling us something about what Jesus is about to do. Because when
we talked about theophany, we mentioned all this language of the Jordan River, parting
and splitting and turning back, right? Which, as we were pointing out, did not literally
happen at the point when Christ was baptized. Because if it had, he wouldn't have actually
gotten baptized because he wouldn't have gotten wet. But that...
language in our hymns and readings and that kind of thing was intended to help us connect
that event of Jesus baptism in the Jordan to the Jordan parting in front of the Israelites with
Joshua when they came in to conquer the land and how part of what's going on in Theophany is that
with his baptism. And Jesus is entering the land.
take it back to sort of a reconquista of the land.
But this fasting period, which is in each case directly associated in the gospel narrative
with his baptism, tells us something about how he is going to retake Israel.
Thank you.
What some of, at least some of, the Judeans would have been expecting Jesus to do as
the Messiah would have been all those people who, St John the 400 just baptized, he's going
to gather them up and turn them into an army and go start killing Romans and Jewish collaborators
while he's at it.
Right.
That would have been one view.
We take the land by.
Killing the Gentiles, right? Killing taking out right the enemies of the people
But what this shows us this callback
To Moses that second time on Mount Sinai
Not eating or drinking anything for 40 days, right? Why did he do that? Why was he up there?
He was repenting
For the sins of the people
Since he didn't participate in personally. Yeah, right
You
but repenting for their sins.
And so that shows us that this retaking of Israel that Christ is about to do is going to have a very different mode
than it did under Joshua.
Than anything you read about in first Maccabees.
Yeah, this is like Moses.
Right. Like that he's like the prophets.
He's going to come and he's going to bring the forgiveness of sins to these people.
not just the Israelites who are otherwise righteous,
not just the collaborators, the tax collectors,
right, the sinners, but even to the Romans.
Right, even to the hated Romans.
He was going to bring the possibility
of forgiveness of sins.
Another 40 days, if we didn't say 40 days and 40 nights,
if we just said 40 days,
Probably an answer that would be high up the list would be the time from Christ's resurrection to his ascension among church goers.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Christ's ascension is 40 days after his resurrection during that period of time he is appearing to people.
Right.
But then it's 40 days again tells us something.
Right. It tells us something.
It's hell.
There's some kind of anticipatory element that there's something more coming and we're
going to end up talking about this more in our second and third halves tonight.
But Christ's resurrection itself, even the ascension itself, is anticipatory of something
else that is coming. And then just to sort of round out our
tour through the Bible with the number 40.
So we could say we went from Genesee to Revelation
in Revelation 11, verse 2 and 13, verse 5. The period of time
where the Antichrist has power, the Beast has power, is 42 months.
Seeing you're counting how many verses we've looked at and hoping it's 42, but
I don't think it...
Yes. We can round a little bit. We can, you know,
just have to be precise. Yeah.
3036, you know.
Right. And so again, that's anticipatory of what's going to come after.
Right. And the end of that rule that it is not the ultimate, right, rule or authority.
So we've gone through all these stories in the Bible, all these verses, all these passages.
What does it all mean?
Seriously, Colin with your ideas. Oh, yeah, yeah, because otherwise I could just go home today. Yeah
So the key thing here is what we've seen from all these examples
Hopefully he is a couple of themes emerging number one
40 40 days
being emblematic in the scriptures for a period of preparation, of anticipation,
something coming, something happening. And then in addition to that, related to
that is this idea of 40 days as a period of repentance, often connected
directly with fasting as a means of repentance.
a discipline of repentance and that these ideas and elements are sort of mixed together
around the idea of 40 days in the scriptures.
And so when we come back in the second half, we're going to start talking about how this
connects to the idea of baptism beyond what we've already talked about.
Man spoilers usually don't give things spoilers like that
It's the first time.
Well, I want to keep them.
I want to keep them around.
It might have been template to wander off somewhere.
Already, I know.
Change that channel.
I'm a wilderness.
Yeah.
We're about to go to a commercial break.
People flip channels during commercials.
It's going to adjust that dial.
Yeah, no, this is actually, this first commercial is going to be a big announcement.
So yeah, we're going to go ahead and take our first break and we'll be right back with
the second half, the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
With the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen
Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF radio.
Yeah, longest commercial ever.
Pretty sure father Steven went out for Keynes Chicken.
Did you get me any?
No, and I still can't believe you're unilaterally
cancelling Lord of Spirits to do that shifters at Rick Roll guy.
I know.
I've had all these.
Yes, people are excited.
People get excited when we talk about cancelling podcasts.
Yeah.
Now they're gonna let that sit out there. That's amazing.
Man, you're gonna get some e-vails.
Oh, totally. Yeah.
People just have to check, you know, in two weeks, like, is there, is there
another episode coming you guys or like, I want to keep doing it, but you're
like, no, no, I'm done.
I want to hang out with Ricky Ray Hall.
I'm going to cancel you before you cancel me if that is his real name.
You know, yeah, it's Richard Roland who, I mean, the world's only living
Rick Roll. I mean he's an
actual Rick Rawl, like his parents made him into that. Which, I mean, that's incredible.
So yeah, yeah. Yeah. All right. Well, anyway, welcome back everybody. So the first half we talked
about the number 40 and showed the many places that it shows up in both the old especially
and new testaments and that 40s and 42s designate preparation for something coming and also are
associated in many cases with.
fasting and repentance and forgiveness of sins. So all right. So what are we doing this half,
father? I forget. No. Oh, no. So I mean, that was a long commercial. Like it was longest
one ever. Yeah. Like I wrote a book and got a master's degree during that commercial.
Yeah.
As one does.
So, right, so now we're moving on.
as mentioned to talk about how this relates to baptism.
And how repentance relates to baptism, or at least the fact that it does,
is probably fairly obvious to people, when we first encounter baptism as such in the New Testament.
And if you want more
this you can go back to our baptism episode. In terms of the difference between baptism as such
and Jewish ritual washings in general, right? When we first encounter baptism as such, it's St. John
the Forerunner, St. John the Baptist, or St. John the Baptist, as I see people liking to put now,
just because they can't bear to use the term baptist.
Yeah, it only be a
Baptist. We're looking out for you, our Baptist friends. We'll still call him St. John
the Baptist sometimes. We're not seeing John the Presbyterian. I'll tell you what. Yeah.
More Methodist for that matter. So it's with St. John and we're explicitly told right
of the bat, like in Mark 1 verse 4, right? That John comes, he's preaching a baptism of
repentance and the forgiveness of
Yeah, like in those words, that's what his baptism is all about.
Baptism is all about repentance and the forgiveness of sins.
They say the people went down into the water, confessing their sins, right?
Publicly, he's baptizing sort of notorious sinners, which is why a lot of the Pharisees
aren't happy about it or at least accept themselves from it because they are not notorious
centers in their mind.
at least. And so they are not like those people. But that is, that is what baptism is all about.
And of course, there's an obvious, pretty obvious, when you're reading any of the Gospels,
presentation of what St. John is doing as preparatory.
as leading to something else, right?
It is everywhere the Gospels presented as,
this is leading up to Jesus appearing on the scene,
being baptized by St. John,
Christ then having his ministry, right?
And the Gospels go from there.
So that's obvious preparatory element.
Calling him St. John the Forerunner
kind of emphasizes that preparatory element.
But this isn't just something that the Gospel writers do.
And it's important to say this because the presentation you get from even to this day,
from most New Testament scholarship, it tries to present St. John, the historical St. John,
right? As a rival of the historical Jesus. This is what they're going to try and sell you on.
And they're going to point to the mandians which are small.
obscure cult, not really obscure. Yeah, small obscure
Nostocult that held that that St. John was the Messiah and hold
that out as evidence of something in the first century. And
say, yeah, and so they're going to say that what the
gospel say about St. John is revisionist history. That they're
sort of making up these stories where St. John was like, Oh,
Don't know
not me him, right, to try and persuade people, right, to, to, to, although Jesus instead, right.
Excuse me. So, all that is, of course, boncom. Right, there is, there is no basis for that other
than just a hermeneutic subspecion. Right. Right. And I think the mandyans, I mean, it's been a
long time since I researched them, although...
moment. They are mentioned in the 2017 edition of orthodoxy and heterodoxy.
Shameless self-promotion to part. There you go. I mean, I'm the Stanley of orthodoxy on
that and then excels here. Yeah, I mean the Mandians as far as I recall, I think some
of the earliest mentions of them that are that anyone knows of is like medieval. I mean,
It's not that far back, honestly.
Yeah.
There are also gnostic sex that had like Hercules as the Messiah and stuff.
Oh yeah.
So it's fun stuff.
I suppose this means the historical Hercules.
Anyway.
Right.
But there is of course this hermeneutic of suspicion, the practice of which was very popular
in the latter half of the 20th century, especially.
I think people are starting, but that may be wishful thinking on my part that people are
collectively starting to
away from it now, but I see a trend of people starting to get away from it now, which is
just to say what we what I mean by hermeneutical suspicion is that when you read the text of scripture,
you assume that the person writing it has some kind of agenda.
Yeah, they're lying to your trying to manipulate you in some way.
Right. Well, even if they're not outright lying, they have a goal and that is I need to convince you
of X. Yeah, I can't remember where it was.
but I think it was C.S. Lewis who said something like,
if you see through everything,
then you're actually seeing nothing.
Yeah.
Which I like that.
It's like if Superman's exhibition went crazy,
he couldn't see anything.
Yeah, I mean, right.
Whereas, so there's this story,
there's this great Superman story
where the Joker like Kidnapps, Lois Lane and Perry White
and Jimmy Olson,
and he says, I'm gonna hide them in lead line cassette.
caskets. So Superman can't find them. Let's see that's dumb because like what
Super Ante turned on his X-ray vision, he can't see through lead. So that's like the only thing he can't see.
But he can pull it apart with a super strength. So he finds them very quickly.
We actually do have a caller by the way who has questions. I hope it's not about that.
No no it's
It's, I mean, I'm trying to figure out, so this is Nathaniel, who's here in Pennsylvania.
I am trying to figure out if Nathaniel's question is a Douglas Adams reference.
So Doug, I hope so.
I hope so.
So Nathaniel, are you there?
I mean, are you, is this Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy kind of thing or?
Yeah, good evening, Father.
Father's bless.
Good evening, God bless you.
and I'm actually a healing doctor.
from Pennsylvania, unfortunately, but neighboring CBN, so extra blessings are needed down here.
Well, your phone is from Pennsylvania. I'll just say that.
Yeah, yeah, phone is from Pennsylvania. That's for sure.
But yeah, I'll start with the Douglas Adams reference.
In light of the first half, can we determine what the meaning of life is, and that is 42.
Yeah, I mean, to me, it seems like Douglas Adams doesn't know everything we just said
at the first half.
If like, that's the meaning that would, you know, the 42s are preparation or is the answer
being 42, preparatory to the finding of the question.
Hmm.
How there it is.
Awesome.
Wadley timey one.
stuff to be. Yeah. Okay. Thank you. Yes. I think you had a more serious question
along along with that one. Yeah. Yeah. No, one question per person. Thanks to think. Oh,
man, you wasted six billion years or whatever.
So the other question had to do with the number seven, naturally. And that is why
the number of.
heavenly bodies is used as the number for fulfillment,
or maybe better put, by the number of the divine council
uses the number to symbolize fulfillment.
I think I know what you're saying,
but I'm gonna just go ahead and punt.
Okay.
Well, yeah, the number of the divine council is 70 or 72.
Right.
Yeah, yeah.
Because of the nations, the number of the nations.
Right.
Well,
actually goes the other way. But yeah, yeah. So, um, so I mean, those are related, obviously,
70 and seven, right? Yeah, seven ends and then seven. And if you look at, um, so Kineha
Form doesn't really have numerals either. You didn't know this is where this was going to go.
but can you form...
writes when you look at like a a barter list or a trade document that's in Kineha Form on a clay
tablet. The way they do numbers is not with letters because it's pictographic. So they put like
hash marks, they don't cross at five. Right, you don't even mean by hash marks, right? You do one,
one, two, three, four and then you do the fifth one across.
They don't go.
across it five. So it's just like hash, tally marks, right, all the way across. There could
be 12 of them, 50 of them, right? But they're all working on prison time. Yeah.
Marking on the wall. So that's one. And then tens were circles. Right. So on a Kineiform
tablet, seven of something would be seven hash marks. 70 of something would be seven circles.
So the way these were written and expressed, and the way things were counted, made a tight
connection between those two things.
So I think if you asked an ancient person like why seven for the heavenly bodies rather
than 70 for the gods.
They would say some version of Porque Nolo's dose in
Acadian. They would they would they would not see why
there needed to be an ore there. I see. Okay. So I went
right here, seven rings. That's that's for the dwarf lord
Lord in their halls of stone.
That or or Marvel seven
movie. Oh, that's 10. The
seven rings. That's 10. The
Mandarin has 10 rings, my
friend.
I'm not cut up on my my
Marvel war.
Busted. See, I thought you
were referring to the legend
of the seven rings, which is
digging in the crates,
tabletop gaming right there.
But I'll take my my
dwarven rings over that.
Although some of them were
consumed by dragons, so
So
just I mean we'll just consider we'll just consider it all them fallen okay
all right well I hope that helps it yeah all right thank you okay well that
went in all kinds of places yeah yeah doesn't know how many rings the
Mandarin has though that's I know
Primony Pete total amateur
Yeah. Next year, tell me you'll be older as seven ice stocks.
Bish.
So right. So we're talking about how
St. John's baptism kind of had both elements that we were talking about with 40.
It had this preparatory element, right.
And obviously it's a baptism of repentance.
But for example, St. Paul and Acts 19 verse four, which is one of his defenses when he's
done.
trial, he talks about St. John baptizing and how that was preparatory to the coming of Christ,
which is further evidence by the way that this is part of the apostolic preaching and
not the product of some kind of historical rewrite that we should be suspicious of.
But there's also this contrast made by
Saint John himself
Between the baptism that he's performing in the Jordan River and
The baptism that the Messiah the Christ who is coming is going to perform
And you can see that for example in Matthew 3 verse 11 Mark 1 verse 8 Luke 3 verse 16
Order your VHS copy of Mark of the Beast 2
from Chuckles, Stedar, our announcer.
There's like 12 people who just had flashbacks.
But in all of those, there is this comparison made where Christ, the Messiah, is going to
baptize with the Holy Spirit and or fire.
where this element is going to be added to baptism, or there is going to be this second baptism.
And what we see early on in the book of Acts, in Acts 2, verse 38, when St. Peter is preaching,
right, he says, be baptized for the forgiveness of your sins, and you will receive the Holy Spirit.
So he has drawn those two things together.
He's drawn.
together the meaning and significance of the baptism that St. John is doing and this baptism
that Christ is going to do and pulled them together in Christian baptism. Already very early
right on the day of Benagost.
St. Peter's pulled these together.
So, for you sometimes,
lose
site of the fact that baptism is preparatory, baptism itself, being baptized is preparatory.
What do I mean by that? Well, especially among our Protestant friends, there is a tendency
disease salvation as something that happens at a point in a time.
An event.
And I think it
It's probably more characteristic of Protestants
that would be defined as low church,
but still, some of the higher church ones
will just use the word justification.
And it's just as much as of an event
as the baptized and saved,
once saved always saved,
kind of thing.
Right, and then, and then depending on
where you are right in the wild wild world of Protestantism. People will have different
views of how that event, whether they call that event justification or call it just salvation
or call it being born again or whatever you want to call that event. How that event is
related to your baptism. So if you're in a church like the Lutheran church that believes
in baptismal regeneration.
kind of the same thing, right? Baptism is where that event happens. If you're in a more
low church setting, then baptism might just be a symbol or a public proclamation
that the event has happened. Yeah. Right. That follows on the event.
But in all of those cases, right, regardless of how exactly baptism is related,
it.
Baptism either is the thing or it's the mark after the fact that the thing has happened and so now that's kind that part is done
Right that part is done
But that's not
really
the perspective of
The scriptures particularly the New Testament particularly Saint Paul on what's going on in baptism
Right.
In places like Roman 6 verse 4 and Colossians 2 verse 12 and lots of other places, but those
are two examples.
St. Paul in talking about baptism talks about it in terms of death and resurrection, both
the death and resurrection of Christ and then our death and resurrection, that in our baptism
we die and then we rise again to new life. Right?
But even that way of framing it, right, that way that St. Paul frames it means that it's
not that baptism is something unto itself or that baptism is the end of something or the
testimony to something that has already happened, but that it's the beginning of something.
It is precisely the beginning of a new life, right?
new and not just a new life in the sense of, oh, now you're
to have eternal life in the age to come. But the beginning of a new life lived differently
here in the world, right, within the church community, within the Christian community,
in the world, in your family, right, that baptism marks this beginning of that.
Yeah, you're not just waiting until you get raptured out or, you know, great tribulation
and comes or whatever.
Right, and I think the comm-
even evangelical rejection of infant baptism is precisely related to this.
If you see baptism as an ending as a culmination of something,
then administering it to an infant who hasn't done anything,
thought anything, agreed to anything, believed anything, thought much.
Right.
Does it make a lot of sense?
Yeah.
because it's what's culminating in the life
of a newborn baby.
Right, I mean, technically they just had
the culmination of gestation, but that's about it.
Right?
But whereas, whereas if you understand baptism
to be the beginning of a new life,
of a new way of life, a new way of living
and being in the world, of being in community,
of being in a Christian family, of living as a Christian,
If it's a beginning.
that it makes perfect sense for Christian families to baptize their children.
Right? It makes perfect sense for their life as a Christian to begin right there,
because they're living in a Christian family as part of a Christian community, going to church.
Right? Why would they live as a heathen? Right? For some period of time. Right?
It doesn't make sense if you're viewing it from that perspective.
But so let's let's talk more about how baptism is presented as preparatory as a beginning, right?
So to flesh out when when St. Paul is using
these terms of death and resurrection, the end of an old life in the beginning of a new life, right?
the idea of
death and the end of that old life is really the idea of repentance. It's a way of talking about repentance.
Right. And he's going to use this language of putting off the old man and even killing it, right?
The right. And this is this is one of these places where kind of dumb, dumb level
gender inclusivity doesn't so wrong. Interpreting the Bible. There are places
There are places, even in the Bible, where being a little bit gender-inclusive makes sense.
Sure.
You know, because they're, for example, there are different words in Greek for a man, a male human, right?
An adult male human, right? A man.
And the word for, like, mankind, humanity, right?
Now, yes, both mankind and humanity include...
the word man in them, right? But I don't think translating it as humanity is some kind of weird,
liberal progressive something or other when we're talking about anthropose. It's a way of distinguishing
it in English, right, from an ear, a man, a male human, right? So, yeah, let me tell you my favorite
story.
though, as a digression about gender inclusivity gone awry.
Okay.
There is an amazing, say not, not where I thought we were going
to night, but I'm, yeah, I'm just going to throw this out
because I find it richly entertaining.
So a lot of this, the gender inclusivity thing started in
the 1970s.
I know many of you were not alive that.
I know.
But you started getting this whole thing where, you know,
Someone would say, you know, when a man...
does this they say, well, or a woman, right? You know, you'd get that, right? That was sort of how the
gender inclusivity thing started. Yeah. And so people kind of got trained by the culture to just say,
a man or a woman, right, when a man or a woman becomes a doctor, you know, when a whatever, right?
And so there was this great moment where this football player named Deacon Jones,
So, now, let's see if we can see the difference.
Failure over M.
Part of what he was famous for was he'd line up opposite somebody.
And then when the play started, he would just take his hand and smack the side of their helmet.
Right.
Like to knock them, to knock them off balance, right?
As the play started to give him an advantage.
So there was this moment where somewhat an interviewer asked Dika Jodes about this.
And Diggit Jod said, well, whenever you go upside the head of a man.
or a woman. Wow. Yes. And sort of it got very quiet in the interview.
As he kind of realized what he said. Yeah. So see, you don't always have to be gender inclusive.
Well, I'll go very long for you. According to the interwebs, he coined the term SAC
to refer to that particular maneuver in football.
Yeah.
So.
So yes, gender inclusivity can go very badly.
And it does us wrong here too,
getting back to the topic in hand.
Because, and I've even seen this
in some recent Orthodox service books.
Like why am I going off on a little rant
about gender inclusivity?
Cause I've seen this in recent Orthodox service books
where like in the baptismal liturgy,
it will use this language of St. Paul's
about putting off the old man.
Yeah.
And you get people who are like, well, what if you're baptizing a girl or a woman?
Right?
But the point here is, St. Paul is not just referring to like the old person, the person you
used to be.
And let me say, killing off the old person does not read well in liturgical text.
We do want to sound like we're promoting euthanasia.
Church, right? We're not Canadians. Oh, jeez. But, right. But the old man in this case is
is a reference to Adam. Yeah. Yeah. The old Adam. Yeah. Right. So Adam, as we've talked about
on the show, right, receives the garments of skin, he receives mortality, right, mortal
flesh.
And we all are born in the likeness of Adam of the old man.
We are born in his likeness.
We also are mortal.
We're conceived mortal.
And because of our mortality,
Our thumbs are weakness to this sinful passions.
How?
is that relate? Right? Well, because I am mortal, there are things that I need. Because
if I don't get them, I will die. Right? If someone is immortal, they don't need anything.
They're immortal. Right? They won't die. But if you're mortal, you need certain things
that you will die. So I need to eat to stay alive. Right? Hunger by itself is what we
We call it Blameless.
passion. It's not sinful to get hungry. Right? It is normal because of my mortal flesh. Right?
But the fact that I need to eat opens up the temptation to the sinful passion of gluttony.
Because I am mortal, I need to sleep. Getting tired is a blameless passion. There's nothing
think sinful about getting tired, right?
But getting tired and needing to rest.
opens up the sinful passion of sloth, of laziness.
It opens up that temptation.
Immortal people don't need to make more people.
Yeah. The world must be people. Therefore, mortal people must make more people.
There is nothing sinful about a husband and wife making more people.
But needing to do that opens up this temptation to the sin of lust.
And we could go on and on, right? I need to have money to pay for shelter and clothing that
opens up greed, right? On and on, our mortality makes us prone to sin and indulging these desires,
these desires of the flesh.
Right? And so the old man, the
old life, pre-baptism, pre-Christ, pre-death in the death and resurrection paradigm,
is a life that's lived seeking to fulfill the desires of the flesh, and even go beyond fulfilling
them, to indulging them. So then, if that life, that old man,
That dies.
Then there's a new life and that new life
that begins at baptism.
St. Paul will refer to as the new man.
Specifically you put off the old man you put on the new man.
Yeah, and this is again where the gender inclusivity thing
right messes it up because it's not the new person.
Right, the new person or the new woman, right?
You're a whole different person now, right?
I'm a new woman.
Yeah, no, it's Christ.
Christ is the new man.
And Adam is the old man.
Like there's these are specific men.
Yes.
And so when we're born of water in the spirit,
to quote Christ, referring to baptism,
then we are born in his likeness,
not the likeness of the old man.
And so in Christ, there is a new humanity,
not new in the sense that
It's a completely different species or different creature.
New in the sense that new is pretty much always used
in the scripture, meaning renewed.
Renewed, because of course the image in which the old man,
the image in which Adam was created was Christ.
Yeah, so that is renewed in Christ himself.
And so this new humanity is a renewed humanity.
That means we get
a, a St Paul will say, a new nature, which is again a renewed nature. But we've talked
about what nature means. Nature like body is a nexus of powers and potentialities. And
so there is a renewed and new set of powers and potentialities that a person has in Christ
that they didn't have...
before. Potentials like immortality, right, like eternal life. And so that culminates in a
new body in the full orbed sense, right, in the resurrection, right? Which again, we believe in
the body resurrection, bodily resurrection, that new body is a renewed body.
Renewed, restored, but now with a new set of powers and potentialities.
And so this new way of life, St. Paul is going to talk about as living according to the
spirit, the Holy Spirit, capital S spirit, not spiritual in some vague sense, but the Holy
spirit, the spirit of God dwelling within us. And that old life is walking according
to the flesh, yeah, right? Following the flesh, seeking to indulge
its desires. And so after our baptism, the new life that begins,
we have these two ways that we can follow. Yeah. And this is made
explicit by Saint Paul in Romans chapter eight. So I'm going to read
verses three through 13. For God has done what the law weakened by
the flesh could not do.
By sending his own son in the likeness of sinful flesh and for sin, he condemned sin in the
flesh, in order that the righteous requirement of the law might be fulfilled in us, who walk
not according to the flesh, but according to the Spirit.
For those who live according to the flesh set their minds on the things of the flesh, but
those who live according to the Spirit set their minds on the things of the Spirit.
For to set the mind on the flesh is death, but to set the mind on the Spirit is life and
piece for the month.
that is set on the flesh is hostile to God, for it does not submit to God's law,
indeed it cannot. Those who are in the flesh cannot please God. You, however, are not in the flesh,
but in the Spirit. If in fact the Spirit of God dwells in you. Anyone who does not have the Spirit
of Christ does not belong to him. But if Christ is in you, although the body is dead because of sin,
the Spirit is life because of righteousness. If the Spirit of him who raised Jesus from the
the dead dwells in you. He who raised...
Christ Jesus from the dead will also give life to your mortal bodies through his spirit who dwells in you.
So then brothers, we are deaders, not to the flesh to live according to the flesh.
For if you live according to the flesh, you will die. But if by the spirit you put to death the deeds of the body, you will live.
And so,
These concepts are important to understand.
stand, what it means when we're talking about a setisism and when we talk about the mortification
of the flesh, right?
Mortification, you could probably tell, if you know any Latin at all, mort is dead, right?
The putting to death of the flesh.
So a lot of people now, when they hear mortification of the flesh, they interpret that as,
Oh, this is some kind of gnostic thing.
Yeah, like it's antibody, anti-material, you know, and sometimes it's distorted to like,
you know, I have to hurt myself, you know, like self-flagulation, which is, I mean, that's
a real thing that exists, exists especially in the Middle Ages and the West.
Right.
It's a thick, inflicting pain or suffering on yourself physically that somehow the physical
You
bad, um, all of these things. And so with that, I'm saying the
modification of the flesh, then asceticism is looked at in
that way that asceticism is about saying the material is bad,
right, or sinful or evil. Yeah, no, it's about handing over
control to the spirit of God versus the desires of the fleshly
body. Right, right. And and so what when when the orthodox
Church at least.
talks about putting the death of flesh, the more efficacious of flesh, they're getting
that from what we just heard from St. Paul.
He used that language.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
And it's talking about subjecting, controlling, right?
In one place, St. Paul says he beats his body with blows.
He doesn't mean that literally in this self-lagilation inflict pain on your self-sense.
It means he gets it under control.
So why St. Paul's always using these athletic metaphors?
about training and physical discipline, right?
You have to get your mortal flesh under control
so that you're not indulging its desires.
You're controlling those desires, right?
And this is a very, this is a very practical thing, right?
So if we're talking about just looking at some
of the examples I gave, right?
If we're talking about food, right?
We need the...
eat to live that opens us up to this temptation to overindulge. Right? In eating, how does
one overcome that? How does one begin to discipline that desire and bring it under control to
get self control and self mastery? How does that happen? Fasting. Right? Fasting is how
you do that. You take control of what you eat for a period of time. Right? And that helps
build that discipline. You don't starve yourself to death.
Right right you don't starve yourself to death. This is one of the things that you really notice
When you read the church fathers well
When you read some of the works of the church fathers that people don't normally read everyone wants to read
The works of the church fathers that are about like the Trinity and Christology so they can have online debates about it
But when you read the works of the church fathers that are dealing with the Christian life which is most of it
And when they're comparing the way Christians live to the way various heretical groups and pagan groups live,
what you find is, if your view of asceticism is harming yourself,
then the mannequins, the nostics, these people have it all over Christians.
These groups would literally fast to the point of death.
They would walk around pale and weak and they considered that a mark of their holiness.
Right. Modern people who get into dosticism for some reason always ditch the asceticism.
It's sort of like there was back in the 90s there was this whole Celtic spirituality fad.
Right.
With people just got really into Anya or something and decided they did to make a religion out
of it.
It was vaguely Christian.
Wow.
Um.
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
So stop me when I tell a lie.
Anyway, um, it was fascinating to be about it.
Or one of the things at least was that if you actually look at Celtic Christianity,
it had one of the most brutal penitential systems in the history of Western Christianity.
And for some reason, the Celtic spirituality folks had none of that.
Yeah.
No one standing in freezing rivers the whole night long reciting the Psalter from memory.
It's not-
Can't smoke weed while you're doing that.
So that tends to get left out.
There's a big difference between that and not eating meat and dairy for forty days.
Those are not the same thing.
They're not remotely the same thing.
Right?
It's not gonna harm you,
especially if you live in Southern Louisiana
and there's seafood everywhere in its delivers.
And like crawfish season is during length every year.
But even for the rest of you who are not so blessed
as to live in God's country, it's not going to kill you.
Some people even eat better and eat healthier
during length and some people eat nothing but carbs.
But it's either way, right?
This isn't harm.
yourself. This is about discipline. And sleep laziness, you have vigils. You have going to church
more. You have spending more time in prayer. Giving alms, giving to the poor, making a special effort
to do that, right? It helps you discipline how you spend your money, right?
how you spend or waste your time, right? These are all means of developing discipline and self-control
and putting to death the sinful desires of the flesh in order to follow the Spirit instead, right?
And another good, I mean, St. Paul talks about this a lot, but another good place, part of which is,
I think, familiar to people.
He talks about this in Galatians, and he talks about these two ways.
that you can go in terms of the fruit that they produce, in terms of what you have in your life
when you either follow the desires of the flesh or you follow the Holy Spirit.
Yeah, yeah, and I mean this is where the rubber meets the road people.
So, all right, so this is Galatians chapter 5 verses 16 through 24.
But I say walk by the Spirit and you will
not gratify the desires of the flesh. For the desires of the flesh are against the Spirit,
and the desires of the Spirit are against the flesh, for these are opposed to each other
to keep you from doing the things you want to do. But if you are led by the Spirit, you
are not under the law. Now, the works of the flesh are evident. Sexual immorality, impurity,
Injuality, idolatry, sorcery, enmity, strife, jealousy, fits of...
anger, rivalries, dissensions, divisions, envy, drunkenness, orgies, and things like these.
I warn you, as I warned you before, that those who do such things will not inherit the
kingdom of God.
But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, patience, kindness, goodness, faithfulness,
gentleness, self-control.
such things, there is no...
law. And those who belong to Christ Jesus have crucified the flesh with its passions and desires.
It's a great, great passage. Yeah. So uh, and you also in the middle there,
described my typical Saturday night. No, I'm, I'm kidding. I don't, I don't engage. I don't. Which first?
So yeah, so
Baptism, right, is about making this beginning.
Before baptism, right, someone in Galatia,
especially someone who's not Jewish in Galatia,
right, is living a life as a pagan,
following their passions and the desires of their flesh, right,
engaging in all those things he talked about,
including idolatry, sexual immorality, sorcery, all those things, right.
Now they're coming.
and they're going to be baptized.
And that flesh is going to die and they're going to come to new life when they receive
the Holy Spirit.
And they're going to begin a new life.
But even after they're baptized and they begin this new life, it's going to be possible
for them to yield and start following the desires of the flesh again.
You may have noticed this.
Listeners.
have been baptized, that even afterwards, right, you are still tempted and even fallen to sin, right?
And so there's still, yeah, there's still this choice that has to be made on an ongoing basis,
not just once, right? But over and over again, to continue to follow the spirit and not yield to
the desires of the flesh, right? But as these people approached baptism,
Right? As they were going to be baptized, they were going to be beginning this new life.
They're going to be changing the whole way in which they live in the world, the whole
way in which they see things, the whole way in which they understand the world and other
people and their families. They're going to be joining this new community. They're going
to be worshipping a different God and worshipping in a completely different way. All of these
things are about to change.
And so that necessitated a period of repentance,
that necessitated a period of preparation for baptism,
to prepare to begin this new life.
And that is what originally Catechesis was all about.
Yeah, it wasn't Orthodoxy 101.
Right, it wasn't as memorizing dates.
It wasn't when things happened.
It was a training in a way of living.
Like this is how you repent.
This is how you put aside the fleshly desires.
And take on.
This is what savings.
Yeah, yeah, exactly.
This is what needs to change.
This is how you worship the true God.
This is what the true God is like
unlike the ones you're used to worshiping.
Yeah, it's about how you live,
how you live, like what makes a good Christian.
Yeah.
and how you see the world.
Right. The renewing of your mind, your news, right?
How you see the world, how you understand the world, how you understand what happens to you.
And all of that is going to come to this culmination at the peak of your baptism when you receive the Holy Spirit.
And begin to be able to walk according to the Spirit.
And so there's this period of preparation.
And because early on in the history of the church, people were received into the church.
they were baptized.
on Paska, on the Passover.
Right? That's when it happened.
You have this 40-day period, a period of preparation,
of repentance, of purification,
for those who are about to receive baptism,
receive the Holy Spirit, begin this new life.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
All right. We're going to go ahead and take our second and final break.
break and we write back with the third half of the Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
How do you explain the sacraments? It's easy to say they're mysteries that we have to take on faith or on the authority of tradition,
But that is not.
how the early Christians understood them. To them, and to all ancient people, the idea
that physical objects had spiritual power was very intuitive, whereas modern people tend
to find this difficult, bizarre, or even, un-Christian. This is because we live in an era shaped
by secularism, a way of viewing a world that's incompatible with sacramental thinking. Because
secular ideas are at the heart of our culture, modern people tend to think in secular ways without
realizing it, even the most well-meaning of us.
How then do we...
live in but not be of a secular culture.
We need to understand the enchanted, sacramental way that the early Christians viewed the world,
but we also need to understand secularism.
What is it really?
Where did it come from?
And how does it influence how we think about religion?
Journey to reality, sacramental life in a secular age, breaks down these important issues
in accessible, non-academic language and is an ideal introduction for young readers,
catechumans, and seekers, as well as for any Orthodox Christians who want to deepen
their understanding.
the sacraments.
Welcome back, everybody.
It is the third and final half of this episode.
Is it the final episode?
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Yeah. I mean, it seems kind of weird to make the last episode about Lent, but...
Yeah, it would seem like this episode would be leading up to something.
Yes, well, during our first half, we talked about 40 and 42.
What all of that is about preparation, forgiveness repentance,
And in the second half we talked about baptism, how it connects all of that.
This episode is about Lent.
You might think that it is going to end with an explication of the Christian Passover,
aka Paska, aka Easter.
But that is not what we're ending it with.
No.
The big shocker at the end.
Yeah.
We're going to zig when you thought we were going to zag.
Just what you think you have all the answers, I changed the questions.
As we move.
mentioned right at the end of the second half, almost like it was a segue or something.
Someone's baptism culminates in their receiving the Holy Spirit in the Christmas.
We did a whole episode on that too.
But that is the culmination of the right.
In fact, the baptism is preparatory for it.
The baptism is purification to receive.
to receive the Holy Spirit.
So if then, as we talked about, the apostles see baptism as connected to the death and resurrection
of Christ, but that is preparatory to the receiving of the Holy Spirit, then that would mean
that PASCA and the ASAN
our preparatory to Pentecost.
Big reveal.
So here in the third half, we're talking about Pentecost.
Yes.
And we're going to look at it.
I think we did a Pentecost episode.
Yeah.
Or might just be thinking of the Christmas episode.
No, we did.
I'm trying to remember the name of it now.
And I think it's called an immaculate dwelling place.
So we did, we did do it.
Oh, yeah, it's episode.
But it was about tabernacles and temples
I'm sorry.
Yeah, well now we're coming at this from a different angle. Yeah.
Because we're coming at this from the angle of observance, right?
And so it may sound weird, right?
Pasca is the feast of feasts, right?
That's over as the feast of feasts and pass over in the in the Torah, obviously.
Well, maybe not, obviously, but is presented at, you know, this will be for you the first of
months, right? This is the beginning of it.
This is the day.
The idea that that's preparatory.
to another feast, especially one that a lot fewer people attend, frankly. Yes.
There's a later this summer when they're on vacation. May seem counterintuitive and odd.
But let me say that it maybe should not be so. Because, for example, when Christ
in St. John's Gospel before his.
death and resurrection is talking to his
Disciples soon to be apostles
About what comes next he talks to them about going away and he's not talking about going away
IE dying and then he's gonna rise again. He's talking about going away is in the ascension
Yeah, is in returning to his father
being enthroned in the heavens
Yeah, and he presents this not as
as
Well, okay, then everything will be done and will be complete.
But he presents that as preparatory to something else.
Yeah.
He says essentially it's going to be better, superior.
Yes.
So, yeah, so this is what he says.
This is John 16, starting in verse 4.
But I have said these things to you that when their hour comes you may remember that I told
them to you.
I did not say these things to you from the beginning because I was with you.
But now I am going to him who's...
me and none of you asks me where you're going. But because I have said these things to you,
sorrow has filled your heart. Nevertheless, I tell you the truth. It is to your advantage that I go
away. For if I do not go away, the helper will not come to you. But if I go, I will send him to you.
And when he comes, he will convict the world concerning sin and righteousness and judgment.
Concerning sin because they do not believe in me. Concerning righteousness because I go to the
the father and you will see me no longer.
Concerning judgment because the rule of this world is judged, I still have many things
to say to you, but you cannot bear them now.
When the Spirit of truth comes, He will guide you into all the truth, for He will not speak
on His own authority, but whatever He hears He will speak, and He will declare to you
the things that are to come.
He will glorify me, for He will take with His mind and declare it to you.
All that the Father has is mine.
therefore I said that he will take what is mine and declare it to you.
So he's talking about what'll happen when the Holy Spirit comes among all his
heroes.
Yeah.
And that is better than him remaining in this world with the disciples.
Right.
So Christ himself is presenting what he is about to do as preparatory to the coming of
the Holy Spirit, right, to dwell in people.
Right.
course, the Holy Spirit comes 50 days.
after PASCA, after the Passover on Pentecost, hence Pentecost.
That's where the name comes from, that it's 50 days.
50 days is, right, you have 49, which is 7.7s.
Right? So, where a suspension happens on the 40th day,
meaning it's preparatory to something.
It's leading to something.
something. See, we teased this third half all the way back in the first half.
It's Christ's essentially his preparatory to something.
Then we have the 777 and on the 50th day, think about the Sabbath years in the Torah.
In the Torah, you don't just have the Sabbath day, but you have Sabbath years.
Every 7th year is a Sabbath year when they are supposed to let the land rest and trust
in God to provide for them.
We know from later in the Hebrews.
that the Israelites literally never did this,
but they were supposed to on every seventh year.
And then every seventh, seven, after every 49 years,
the 50th year was to be the Jubilee year.
Yeah, where all the slaves get freed,
all the land goes back to over,
it belongs to all the debts get canceled, big reset.
Right.
And so after the seven sevens,
you get this day.
this day. So.
So the cyclical pattern of years in Israel, if they had followed this, would have culminated
in this 50th year.
So the idea here is that the Holy Spirit coming is the culmination of all of this.
But of course, the feast of Pentecost, the feast that's celebrated there is not a new
one.
This isn't.
the Holy Spirit came 50 days after Jesus rose again.
And so there came to be this feast of Pentecost.
This is a Jewish feast.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, just like Pascas they gave Passover.
This is Pascas.
This is a feast from the Torah, right?
And so to sort of fully understand what's going on here,
we have to understand the first Pentecost.
That will help us understand the second pick I've caused.
In the same way that if you understand the first Passover, it helps you understand what's
going on with the second Passover and second Paska and Christ's death and resurrection.
So the first Pentecost is 50 days after the Exodus at Mount Sinai when the Israelites received
the Torah.
It is the liturgical reenactment and participation in that event
when Moses first received the Torah.
Again, we talked about this event back in the first half and how sort of
parentingmatic it is.
And about Moses fasting before the second time that he received it.
But this annual celebration brought the people back to that.
Well, how did...
the people participate in it. So we've talked about on the show before with with the way the Passover was celebrated
Right, and that the how is this night different than every other night. This is the night when God brought us
Out of Egypt right not our ancestors. Yeah us
us so they dress like they're about to go on a journey
They make unleavened bread like they're about to go on a journey
and they don't have time for the Dota RIs.
Right, all of the fists.
Stand.
Yeah.
Yeah. So they are participating in that liberation from slavery in Egypt by celebrating the Passover.
So what were they participating in in particular, right? They're not participating in going
up the mountain with Moses, because the people didn't go up the mountain with Moses. They're
terrified, right? What they were participating in was when Moses read to them the book of
the covenant and they said all of these things you have said we will do.
Which they didn't which they didn't spoilers, but right right but when they agreed
right and
Your average Israelite or your average Jewish person in the second temple period right
Likewise had at many points in their life
Agree that they would be faithful to gods covenant with them that they would be faithful to the Torah and
Guess what spoilers they had been
Thank you.
Right. But on that day, the day of the feast of Pentecost, by participating in that feast,
they could come back and reaffirm. Right? No, I'm going to reaffirm, I'm going to re-dedicate myself
to living my life according to the Torah, to doing those things that God has commanded me to do,
to not doing those things that God has commanded me not to do, to being faithful. Right? As God has
always been faithful to us. Right?
I'm going to commit now again to be faithful to him.
So there's this kind of renewal of the covenant or reaffirmation of the covenant is what they were participating.
And so the second Pentecost, the Pentecost that's related to us in the book of Acts,
right? When the Holy Spirit comes and indwells all of the followers of Christ.
It's described in Acts using language from the new covenant passages of the Old Testament.
Jeremiah 31, Joel 2, Ezekiel, right, other places that talk about there being a new covenant.
Again, new here really means renewed, made new again. But that's connecting this idea, right?
And a very important part of that new covenant language.
was that the Spirit would write the Torah on people's hearts. Instead of the
Torah being written on tablets of stone, instead of the Torah being written in a
scroll, the Torah would be written on the human heart. And that's a move from
external to internal. And if you don't understand this in the New
Covenant prophecies you won't understand.
say what St. Paul is doing when he talks about the Torah, right? This move from external to internal
because for St. Paul, that's the difference. You may have noted in the second half when Father
Andrew was reading those passages from Romans and Galatians, the Torah kept coming up.
I think of that translation. It said law, right? But that's talking about the Torah. The Torah kept coming up.
Right. And St. Paul says, look, if you're living according to the flash, if you're living
to gratify your flesh, you can't keep the Torah. Why? Because if you're following the desires
of your flesh, it's impossible for you to please God. Right? And so St. Paul's assuming that keeping
the Torah is pleasing to God, right? Kind of because God said it was. But, all right. So, you can't do it.
Right? You juxtapose that with what he says about like the fruit of the Spirit.
All of these things that will come into your life when you're following the Spirit
Against which things there is no law. There's no commandment against them
Right you will keep the Torah
Right without trying not as a list of rules written rules the letter of the Torah that is external to you
Trying to just follow these observances as best you can but because it's written in your heart
And you're following the Spirit right and and he's
leading you to produce these things. At one point St. Paul says, the one who loves keeps the whole Torah.
That's just the first of the fruit of the Spirit.
But that's at the core. And St. Paul is not saying something really new there,
right? Like Deuteronomy says that. And Christ quoted Deuteronomy saying that.
This sums up all the law, the prophets love the Lord your God with all your heart, with all your
your mind with all your strength.
or move it against love your neighbors yourself.
St. Paul's just saying the same thing.
Right.
But that makes this distinction.
And that was a distinction that was already present
in the Torah itself when it talks about
in Deuteronomy circumcising your heart.
Right, you can trash.
Yes, you have this external thing
you've been circumcised in the flesh,
if you're male and you're in Israel, right?
You've been circumcised outwardly,
But that's not what's important.
It's a circumcision of the heart that's important.
This is just the same
these same ideas, right?
And so
Even though when you read St. Paul, he makes this clear distinction and talks about, you know, following the spirit is the way you actually fulfill
what the Torah demands of us
right
the narrative of the Holy Spirit.
coming and indwelling people on Pentecost that we read in Acts is saying the same thing. If you
understand this background, this background of the Feast of Pentecost, that that's when the Torah was
given. Right. And the idea of the New Covenant, and this move from external to internal. Right.
Okay.
And the importance of this feast and its celebration.
Right? That it already been seen in its practice as a sort of culmination, not as sort of,
it tends to be looked at as an epilogue to PASCA.
Yeah, the end of the festival cycle now back to quote unquote, ordinary time.
Right. Yeah. That's how a lot of people tend to look at Pentecost, right? And, um,
Um.
I mean, it's harder to look at it that way in the Torah, but I mean, I think people managed
to do it looking back on it retrospectively, to say that, well, Passover is the really
important thing.
I think when you're reading through the book of Exodus, it's pretty clear that the giving
of the Torah is what the Exodus from Egypt is building up to.
Yeah, I mean, the narrative.
Yeah, right.
Like, you leave Egypt, not so that you leave Egypt.
Leave Egypt.
so that you get to sign eye. Right. Right. But so that was that was seen in how Pentecost was
celebrated. And this is testified to by the fact that when we get to Acts 2 and the Holy
Spirit comes at Pentecost, why are there thousands of Jewish people in Jerusalem from all these
other countries and other places? Yeah. Because it's because it's a big deal. Right. Because it's
It's a big deal, so thousands upon thousands of people came to Jerusalem for the...
that feast. Right? So while we may be able to look back and see that clearly, right, and
Exodus, it's far rarer, I think, that we understand that in the New Testament, that we
understand that Christ, death and resurrection and ascension are building up to the coming
of the Holy Spirit. That the coming of the Holy Spirit is the climax of that story, not
an app log to it.
The Holy Spirit coming into Wellington is not something to tie us over until Jesus comes back.
I say that very confidently because Father Andrew read Christ saying that in St. John's
Gospel, right. I'm going out on a limb I know, but I'm going to say Christ was right.
So what then is going on with our
annual celebration of Pentecost, or at least should be going on with our annual celebration
of Pentecost in the church, as opposed to seeing it as an epilogue, we should be seeing this
as the climax of the feasts. And if Pentecost was being celebrated as the renewal of the old
covenant, then we should understand Pentecost as the renewal of the new covenant.
Right?
Not that we received the Holy Spirit again and again and again once a year, right after
we were, after we were Christmas.
But that, any more than they received the Torah over and over again, right?
But that we recommit to living according to the Spirit, to walking according to the
spirit year after year after year because guess what?
Just like those Israelites you and I
Commit to that a lot and don't pull it off
We go after the indulgences of the flesh over and over again and need to come back and recommit
So just to give some examples and
And a lot of this is because
our audience I know likes learning about obscure second-tippled Jewish.
stuff. Some stuff about the importance of the Feast of Pentecost in the Second Temple period,
right? The great importance. So in the Book of Jubiles,
Pentecost is presented as the most important feast of the year,
of the year which might be the surprise.
right, meaning it's presented as more important than Passover, more important than the day of atonement.
Right. It is the most important feast of the year. And it was celebrated by the taking and renewal
of oaths, right, related to the Torah. But a lot of Jubilee's takes place before the Torah was given.
Right. That's why it's oaths in general.
in general. But the way Jubilee's present
the feast of Pentecost is that the feast of Pentecost is eternally happening in heaven.
That is the feast that is eternally happening in heaven.
Is the feast of Pentecost. Well, what does that mean? The giving of the Torah is eternally
happening in heaven. Well, what they meant by that is that God's commitment to be faithful
to the Torah. God's commitment to be faithful to his covenant is eternal.
Yeah, he's always doing it. Right. Remember what we said about the divine energies a few episodes ago. Right.
God is eternally faithful, eternally committed to his covenant. Right.
We obviously are not. Right. We obviously are not. But he is. So it's eternally happening in heaven.
And then that eternal celebration in heaven touches human time and space reality.
And in the view of Jubilee's, that happens at particular points in time.
Like when God makes his covenant with Noah, that is Noah coming to participate in this
eternal covenant faithfulness, eternal chesed of God.
Right. And then all of the other comments, obviously, the giving of the Torah Mount Sinai is a, is a pream, an example of this.
But then this is also true at the celebration of pentacoste.
year in the cycle. Humans enter into this moment where God is eternally faithful and then we again pledge
to be faithful to God in response at those manifestations in time and space, those points of connection.
So that's how Jubilee presents the book of Jubilee presents Pentecost. As you might expect based
on that.
from the documents we have from Kumron.
Because Jubilee's is the fourth most prevalent text
in the Dead Sea Scrolls had a major influence
in the community in Kumron.
And so, scholars argue whether it was
the most prominent feast in Kumron.
There's an argument to be made for that.
There's an argument to be made for Passover.
It's one of the two.
Right, those are the two big ones.
and then scholars are
you over which one was on top. But we have actually, it's fragmentary, but we have some fragmentary
prayers that they used at the Feast of Pentecost that all involve this reaffirming, not only
of the covenant with God related to the Torah and other covenants, but also the sort of
internal covenant of the community. The bond that...
that particular community had and its structure was seen as sort of an internal covenant that
they were party to and that was reaffirmed on the day of Pentecost.
Phylo talks about a group, a Jewish sect in Alexandria called the Therapute, which, if
If your Greek is really really bad, I will tell you means healers.
Right. And so this group that was focused on healing again for them,
Pentecost was the greatest feast of the year. And what they would do on that day
is they would have a massive meal just this ongoing feast throughout the evening
and the night. And during that feast, they would have this marathon tourist
study and exposition match. People just reading and preaching on
the Torah and studying and arguing about the Torah over this huge expansive meal.
They preach off.
Yeah, because that's what the Torah was given.
Right.
So those are all windows into the popularity and give you some background as to why those thousands
of people were there.
Were there in Jerusalem.
Right.
And so there is this emphasis at Pentecost.
There's this reaffirmation of
of repentance, of the putting off of the old life, of the death of the old man, the crucifixion
of our sinful flesh, in community together.
There is a reaffirmation of our baptisms, not only that death, but also the new life that
comes afterwards. That death and resurrection, not only of Christ but of us in Christ.
Through baptism. There's a reaffirmation of the new covenant as we pledge
ourselves again to walk according to the Spirit, to live according to the Spirit,
not according to the flesh and its sinful desires. And already in Second Temple
Judaism, these kind of community reaffirmations were accompanied by public
Fasting.
Right?
P-
Public fasting is when people fast together.
Right?
Supposed to private fasting, which is when I fast about something by myself.
Periods of community fasting.
Right.
And we can see how this idea and these understandings, right, get incorporated into great
IE, as we talked about at the end of the second half,
there's this...
40-day period of preparation of repentance of purification,
in which those about to be baptized engaged,
before this whole cycle of events, beginning with Christ's death and then his resurrection,
and then his ascension, and then the receiving of the Holy Spirit. They already received the Holy
Spirit in their christmas day, sort of proletically. But this preparation for that
Now we can see, hopefully, now that we've talked a little more here in this third half about
the sort of public and communal act of reaffirmation, of concelebration, of Pentecost, how the
churches a whole began to join in solidarity with those preparing.
This was a natural thing coming out of Judaism.
At the beginning of the...
church, right, that this would be understood in this way. That well, yes, I was baptized
X years ago, right? I'm not preparing to be baptized this year, right? These people are,
but I'm going to join with them in their fasting and in this period of purification and
in this period of expectation. In order to renew and reaffirm what happened in my baptism
And what?
happened in my christmation. And where I'm supposed to go after that, right? What the life that that
was intended to begin, that I have faltered in. Yeah, I mean, and this is this is one of the reasons
why it's a good idea to go to baptisms and christmations, even if it's not somebody that you know,
right? I mean, and I'm sure a lot of people like a lot of married people, for instance, have had
the experience of go.
going to a wedding and it sort of reconnects you to your own wedding and makes you think
about your marriage and all that kind of stuff, you know, like that's all there. You're
reparticipating in that for yourself.
Yeah. Yeah.
Let me be controversial. Let me be controversial.
Baptisms are not family events.
Yeah. No. No.
community events.
person's being introduced into the community.
Yeah, your whole parish should be there.
Yeah, and I mean, just on a practical level,
for a lot of, you know, most orthodox Christians,
I think this is probably correct to say,
most orthodox Christians get baptized
when they're little babies.
And so they have no, you know, conscious memory
of the experience.
And that's another reason why it's a good idea to go
is to renew that experience.
so that you actually do have a conscious...
memory of what all that is like. And you will hear, again, those words that were said
when you were baptized and know that that has been done to you as well.
Yeah. And that's no obstacle to receiving a sacrament, by the way. I have, I have like
zero conscious memory of my wedding. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Those of you who are married
maybe able to identify. I remember I have I have
grueling near PTSD about the wedding planning.
And then the day itself is a blur. Right. And then I was married.
So yeah, right, even if you've had an orthodox wedding, you need to go to another one,
so you could actually hear the prayers. Yeah, yeah.
And think about them.
So that's not something unique to babies being baptized. There's lots of sacraments that go by as a blur.
Yeah.
ordination. Yeah.
I remember that either.
Yeah.
I remember that the people were singing axios too fast.
This is my only memory of my rotation to the priesthood.
The people were singing axios too fast.
And so I was like desperately struggling to keep up in putting on the pieces of vestment.
They're going to give me all axiode out.
Yes, that's the only conscious memory I have is that people were moving way too quickly.
too quickly. The mission kept handing me pieces.
investment that I was like, tying this, trying to get them all on. Yeah.
Where's a somebody can tie. Yeah. So, yeah. So the lots of them are a blur. Right.
But yeah, so this is something we do together as a community and solidarity with the people
who are getting baptized as this reaffirmation, this recommitment as a group. Yeah. Right.
as a group as a whole.
And that brings us to Greenland.
Although, I mean, to be like, if you've listened to the last two hours and 25 minutes and you
didn't connect any of that to Lent, we have to lay that out for you.
I've questioned whether you were really listening.
Yes.
So go back and listen to the whole thing again.
Exactly.
Exactly, exactly.
But yeah, I mean it's it's yeah, yeah
Exactly.
So, well, I mean, to bring some thoughts in here at the end, I remember years ago reading
for the first time, Father Alexander Schmemman's lovely book called Great Lat.
And also, actually, it's been a long time since I've read it.
And it's been a long time since I've read his book for the life of the world.
And so I might be mixing some stuff up.
But they have a lot of comments themes between them as I recall.
But I think one of the things that he says in one of those books and maybe in both of them
is that a lot of people have the sense that the purpose of Christianity of quote-unquote religion
is to help, he uses that word, to help.
Right, like if you ask a lot of people, I mean a lot of words.
with those people, what's the purpose of length?
What's the point of it?
They might say something like, well,
it makes me become a better person, something like that.
It's about becoming better.
And, I mean, on a certain level, that's not wrong, right?
I hope that people emerge from the other end of length
in a better state than they were in the beginning.
But I think that...
the problem with that framing of what's going on is that it looks at it as a kind of
program that fits within the story of my life. And I understand that. I mean, we're all
living in our own lives. And the modern world trains us to think of our lives as being a
story about ourselves that I'm the main character. I'm the hero of this epic tale. But that's
SHUT
not true. It's just not. I mean one of the things about learning to live the Torah in the heart is
learning to live in humility. Humility is that key key virtue from which all the other ones flow.
And if you learn in humility, then you know that if you live in humility, then you know that
the story is not about you. It's not about me. It is Christ's story.
Right? And so seeing that lent is pointing towards Pentecost, that it's preparatory towards
Pentecost, towards being alive and by the Spirit, that it's this great sweep that is about
what Christ is doing for us, to us, for the world,
atonement for the whole world.
Right? That it's that. That gives a different understanding of what's going on.
And then the question is not, you know, how does this make me better?
But rather, where do I fit into this story that is happening without me?
Like, it's happening whether I'm in it or not.
But I can become part of it. I can participate in it. Right?
and
One of the experiences that I've had, and I know other people have had because I
served in pastoral ministry for 13 years, and I still work with people, you know,
because I'm a member of a parish, and I'm still a priest in the parish, is that
when you conceive of great land or any of the disciplinary practices of the church
as being about getting better, as being about self-improvement,
It's really...
really easy to get bogged down and discouraged.
Because you try and you try,
and you might see some progress maybe,
but you might see none.
You might see back and forth,
one step forward, two steps back,
and it's easy to become discouraged.
This is true not just in Great Lent.
It's true in the other...
set of cool
stories of our life
marriage
probably number one for those who are married and i've never been a monk but um i've had monks tell me
nuns tell me that um
it can be that way for them
parenting often feels like one step forward two steps back or you know
one step forward, two steps left.
Two, three steps right.
whatever it might be. All kinds of relationships, all kinds of pursuits can
become very discouraging when we think of it in terms of this is my story.
But it's not my story. Listener, it's not your story. Actually, I have much better
news. It's a crazy story. And that means
that even if in my life, whether it's my experience of great land, my experience of my marriage,
my experience of parenting, my experience of friendship, my experience of ministry, whatever
it might be, whatever it is, whatever it is, whatever is your experience. Even though at certain
points, or maybe even the apparent overall arc, can be discouraging, right? I mean, it's likely
that most of us.
when we die, we'll feel like there's a lot left undone.
Didn't win at the end, not winning now, whatever it might be.
However, that goes.
The point is so that we can enter into preparation for life in the spirit.
in this life and ultimately
in the life of the age to come in the resurrection.
This life is about getting things in order
so that we are prepared for that life.
But it's not about simply waiting until that life starts.
It's about becoming righteous now
through the enlightenment of the Holy Spirit
who gives us the ability to do that,
having the
Torah, the law, the way of God written in our hearts.
Big piece of that is to know the Scriptures.
I mean, you had to ask me what the point of our whole podcast is about is that people
would want to know the Scriptures.
And the more that you know the Scriptures, like way deep down in your bones, the more the
path opens up clearly in front of you.
It doesn't make you walk the path.
you can
and you can learn about this book and not actually do what's in it.
But it becomes clear as to what you should do.
But also, it's not just a manual on the things that you should do.
It's the story, the story, the great story, the last story, the first story.
It's all those things all it wants.
And as we are, most of us, probably most of you listening to this right now,
See you next time.
a few weeks away from land. This year in 2024, it starts on March 18th, a few weeks away
from land. As we begin to enter into that journey, look through it, look towards Paska. Yes,
we're looking for that, but also towards Pentecost, the life in the spirit.
and know that that
That's the point of renewal, true renewal.
And now we're preparing ourselves for that.
And I think that you will discover that whatever ups and downs,
whatever detours, whatever sidetracks, deviations,
failures, the experience between now and then.
And I hope to God, you experience triumphs as well, right?
God give you that consolation.
whatever happens, even if we have to drag ourselves across the finish line to cost,
that we know that we are doing it because we want to participate in Christ and his story,
and his kingdom shall have no end. That's what I have to say about that.
So one of the things I have to tell people
over and over again in confession during a lint.
And you get a lot of people who come to confession during lint who don't always come to confession other times.
But one of the things I have to tell them over and over again that surprises a lot of people at first is
when I tell them that lint is set up for you to fail.
And I kind of say what?
Because invariably, those are the...
first things you get confessed, right?
When you're here in Confessions,
it's, well, I messed up keeping the fast and I didn't,
et cetera, et cetera.
And so I set point out that it's set up for them to fail.
What would succeeding even look like?
I mean, hypothetically, there could be a person out there
who keeps the fast perfectly every moment of length
comes to every single service in their par-
community, empties out their savings account and gives it to the poor, prays during every
waking moment for the entirety of Lent, sleeps three hours a night because they're keeping
vigils staying up late praying for all of Lent. Hypothetically, there could be such a
person. I don't think I've met them. They'd have to do it all in secret too. So I mean,
maybe I have and they don't come to confession because they don't sin.
I don't think that person is out there, right? But let's say hypothetically that person did exist and that was you
Would keeping let perfectly like that be good for you
It would at minimum present a great temptation
to pride
About how well you've kept it compared to everyone else
The very least there would be that temptation.
Well, so that kind of prompts the question, if it's set up for us to fail, then why would
you set up rules that pretty much everyone is going to fail in some way?
In different ways and to different degrees, but everyone's going to somehow fail.
Well, we have to ask again, what is the goal?
we talked about this sort of in the middle of the show tonight.
right? The goal here is self mastery. That's really the goal of the Christian life, right?
To master yourself so that you can be mastered by the Holy Spirit. Because you can't really,
as much as we say it over and over again in the liturgy, to really offer our whole selves
God to really be able to
to do that, we have to first master ourselves. Because if there's some part of my life,
some part of my heart, some part of my soul, some part of my mind that is out of my control,
right? I can't offer that to God. It's out of my control, meaning it's probably deep
into following the sinful desires of my flesh.
So self control that last fruit of the spirit.
I think that may be why it's listed last, because it's the hardest one.
Right?
It's the hardest one.
So how would you develop that?
How do you take control of these things?
Well, we talked about that too.
Right?
If my gluttony is out of control, how do I...
counter that well by fasting. If my laziness is out of control, how do I counter that?
Well, by vigils, by staying awake, by denying myself the kind of rest and leisure that I
want to indulge in. Right? How do I discipline my spending habits? How do I discipline how
I waste time? Right? Let gives us opportunities to do all of that and to fail at it.
And by giving us that opportunity to fail, it shows us the areas where we're weak.
It shows us the areas where we're still out of control.
As an example, one of the questions I get about fasting invariably is, oh, when it says
we can't have wine in oil, does that mean no alcohol or just no wine?
But I always tell people, that means...
alcohol regardless of what the Russians say. That means all alcohol. And I say to them,
here's why I say that because if you can't go 40 days without alcohol, that'll tell you
something about your relationship with alcohol. You will learn something about yourself,
The self-mastery begins with self-knowledge.
So does repentance.
If we don't really know ourselves, we can't get control of ourselves and we can't really repent.
And you say, well, how can I not know myself?
We're into Nile about a lot of things.
We lie to ourselves a lot.
But when it comes down to it, right, I can say, oh, I'm in control of myself all I want.
I can say, no, I make my choices.
No, I'm not controlled by passions.
I'm not mastered by anything.
And then you asked me to eat a peanut butter and jelly sandwich for lunch instead of a ham
and cheese sandwich.
I'm like, I can't do it.
Right?
I've been lying to myself.
So let gives us this opportunity to see all of our weaknesses.
See just how much our life the rest of the year is at a control.
by gaining that knowledge to begin to get a handle on.
controlling it. I sometimes when I'm talking to people compare great length to boot camp in the military.
No one in the military continues to keep the level of discipline that they have in boot camp
for their entire military career. It would kill them. Right, you can't do it. Bootcamp is deliberately
this ultra-intense period of time.
In the same way that we don't tell people, no, you need to keep Great Land all year round.
That would not be a good thing.
It would not be a good thing for you.
But if you go through boot camp in the military, and then when it's over, you forget everything
you learned about yourself, and you discard all of the discipline you developed completely,
and go to see that it was a waste.
There's a waste of time, there's no reason to do it.
and it's true of great life.
If you get to Paska and we all feast at Paska, we all have a party at Paska.
Nothing wrong with that.
We're celebrating, right?
But if everything you learned about yourself during Lent, if all the weaknesses you learned
about, if all the places where you need to do some work, you forget about it, then let
was a waste and you shouldn't have bothered.
But on the other hand, if we remember that, we now have sort of a spiritual curriculum
for the next.
next year. We now have a better idea of what's wrong. Where we need to work. Where we need
to ask for God's help. Where we need to focus our attention. And we have this curriculum
to get us through to the next year. And then the next year there will be great land again.
And there will be another test. And sometimes we'll find out we're still weak in some of the
areas where we thought we were doing a lot better.
And in some cases,
do better in some areas and then worse than others. Because this isn't a one-time thing where,
okay, now I've got it licked. No more sin in my life, but it is an ongoing thing of struggling
to continue to walk according to the Spirit and not walk according to our flesh. And Lent is this
This time of focus, a renewal of recommitment that can sh-
our whole year and through shaping the years of our life end up end up shaping our whole life.
You will get as much out of this great land and every great land as you're willing to put into
and commit to it. If you decide to ignore the fast, if you decide to ignore the extra services,
if you decide to ignore all these things, you're not going to get it with the lightning bolt,
You're actually going to hell for it, but you'll be missing out.
on a whole set of blessings that you could have in your life.
You'll be missing out on the fruit that living according to the Spirit can bring in your life.
You'll be missing out on peace.
You'll be missing out on joy.
You'll be missing out on love that could be in your life.
If you are working to follow the Spirit.
So each of us have...
a choice to make a series of choices during Great Land. Hopefully what we've talked about tonight
in various ways will help all of us as we come to this Great Land to make the right choices
and the harder choices and help us all commit to failing, sometimes failing spectacularly
and in interesting ways in order to learn about ourselves to continue.
to grow and to recommit to following the Holy Spirit who's leading us to Christ.
or you need help finding a parish, head over to orthodoxintro.org.
And join us for a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific.
If I saw something new, I guess I wouldn't worry. If I saw something new, I guess I wouldn't care.
If you are on Facebook, you can follow our page. You can join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere.
But most importantly, share the show with a friend who is going to love it.
And finally be sure to go to ancientfaith.com strokes.
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
You said you're always sleeping,
but if so, I'll be leaving.
It's just that I'm always falling
and it makes me feel bad.
Shugaz for you people.
Thank you, good night.
God bless you and a blessed let to you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and father Stephen Dia-
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne,
and the beasts, and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000,
and thousands of thousands, saying with a loud voice,
worthy as the land that was slain to receive power, and riches,
and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11 through 12